Finding Aid for the S. Charles Lee papers LSC.1384
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Photographs
  - Theatres
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Section, auditorium (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The auditorium section shows the two-tier balcony (40818, 40821) the recessed niche with a sculpture (40820), the wall decoration flanking the proscenium (40819) and the diamond pattern on the side walls of the auditorium.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Perspective sketch, foyer (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The theatre as built closely resembles Lee's renderings. Here the foyer and staircase feature curved and angled walls and a startling rococo-like recessed ceiling panel that was to be lit by indirect lighting. See 40811, 40814.
    - Miscellaneous Theatres. - Newsreel, B.H., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Modesto Theatre - Modesto. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - New Theatre Sketches [Piedmont], Renderings, 8 × 10 photos. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - New Theatre Sketches., 1945. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - New Theatre Sketches: Rio, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      This design makes good use of a small urban lot by maximizing the advertising space. The design above the marquee is one unit, the design below another. The projecting marquee attracts the attention of both Driver and pedestrian. The exterior could be of concrete, plaster, terra cotta, glass or plastic, the lettering in copper or white metal.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Park, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      This theatre is designed with a glass front. The box office has an automobile entrance to the parking lot with an automobile exit on the other side of the building. At night varicolored lights play on the façade and the building forms its own reflective background.
    - New Theatre Sketches: La Vona, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Note on reverse: This theatre shall be its own advertising and the front shall sell the picture. Each row will have different colored lighting arrangements and the whole will be a blaze of color with the new fluorescent lighting units.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Correa, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Lee produced a number of designs for newsreel theatres, a type of theatre that would show newsreels on a continuous basis. All the renderings describe in this archive as Theatre Design Concepts are newsreel theatres. The newsreel had been introduced as a short shown before the feature during the 1930s. World War II heightened interest in the newsreel, giving rise to the idea of small theatres showing newsreels only. As technology allowed, Lee began to increase his use of glass and later plastic, both transparent materials that could be used to great effect for buildings whose primary use was at night. Lee's renderings for these designs all show the buildings at night. By using transparent materials, Lee was creating illuminated sculptures that were their own advertisements for the film.Note on reverse: This modern idea has been designed to be inviting, entertaining and smart, to stand out in a busy location. The name on the theatre indicates the design was prepared for M! exico, probably in early 1940s.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Diana, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Note on reverse: This theatre is designed to be built in plastic; the unusual façade is, therefore, ... ...CHECK ORIGINAL.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Sign, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Note on reverse: This theatre is built with a glass front so the lobby may be viewed from the street. This makes the front entertaining in itself and stresses the fact that entertainment is housed within. The poster cases are designed to sell the show.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Town, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Note on reverse: This spectacular design has been planned to care for a change in theatre patronage. It is meant to speak up to the people to come in and see what is inside, and is planned for a locality where the newsreel has become an attraction.
    - New Theatre Sketches: Pix, Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Note on reverse: This theatre is designed for a residential neighborhood of modern character. It will be built of glass and stone. See the similar Bay Theatre in Pacific Palisades (11301-11310).
    - New Theatre Sketches., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Newsreel Theatre. - Oakland, 1942; Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Lee's rendering depicts an eye-catching marquee, probably with a revolving and illuminated globe, attached to the three-story retail and office building in downtown Oakland (See 50401-50408 for newsreel theatre concepts).
    - Newsreel Theatre. - Oakland, 1942; Existing facade (Box 5, Folder 6)
      This photograph of the existing building in downtown Oakland was the basis for Lee's concept rendering.
    - New Theatre Sketches - Bakersfield. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Palm Theatre. - Palmdale., 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Pantages Theatre. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Facade, night (Box 5, Folder 10)
      The night view shows how the use of neon strips exploited the simple lines of the building, making it a beacon for motorists driving along Pico Boulevard.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Auditorium side wall (Box 5, Folder 10)
      A molded form simulates a gigantic swag of fabric, creating a dramatic frame for the proscenium.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Auditorium rear (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Palms and flamingos are painted in bright paint on the dark side walls. Indirect lighting panels on the ceiling create a softly-lit interior which dramatizes the tropical scenes. Striped upholstery on the seats adds elegance to the simple space.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Auditorium from balcony (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Foyer, candy counter (Box 5, Folder 10)
      This photograph by Shulman reveals a mural on the left wall, the veneered woods below the mural and the sleek lines of the candy counter and popcorn machine.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Foyer entry (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Lee uses curves and indirect lighting to create complexity in the foyer. Julius Shulman's lighting adds drama to the photograph of the space.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Facade, day (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Newly built, the Picwood is set on a main boulevard in a residential neighborhood.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Box office, rendering (Box 5, Folder 10)
      The drawing style, with its curving frame, the simple swept lines of the box office, and the abstract lines on the lobby floor, which use motifs drawn from contemporary painting, all bespeak the era of the 1930s and 1940s.
    - Picwood Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1946; Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 10)
      The Picwood was designed as a neighborhood theatre on Pico Boulevard in West Los Angeles. The design epitomized the modern post-war aesthetic, which required simple lines, inexpensive building materials and quick construction to satisfy the post-war boom. The simple curved pylon was a landmark in the flat landscape of one- and two-story buildings.
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Construction (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Construction photographs show the process of framing and cladding the building, as well as the trucks and equipment used. Interior scaffolding (51103) shows how the frame was supported as it went up. A close-up of the truss detail (51104) shows how the trusses were bolted together. Workmen begin to finish the exterior (51105). The end wall is closed with V-angled boards (51106). Exterior finishing and ventilation ducts are added (51107). People line up at the box office on opening night (51108). The auditorium interior reveals its structural origins; (51109) the trusswork is left exposed in the ceiling. Lee (right) shakes hands with the owner (left) on opening night (51110).
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Auditorium (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Opening night box office (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Construction (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Construction,end wall (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Construction (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Construction interior (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Truss detail (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Opening night,S. Charles Lee (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Puente Theatre. - Puente, 1947-1948; Perspective sketch (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Lee's sketch offers a prototype for a theatre that could be built cheaply and quickly. The simplest means of quickly constructing a theatre-sized space was to build a Quonset hut, a method devised in the late 1930s using small wood members to create an arched truss frame, which was then often clad in metal for warehouse purposes. A number of motion picture theatres were built in this way. They offered inexpensive rapid construction of theatre spaces in small towns such as Puente, an agricultural community east of Los Angeles.
    - Raphael Theatre. - San Raphael., 1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Reforma Theatre - Mexico City, Perspective sketch (Box 6, Folder 2)
      This theatre and office complex, perhaps taking its name from the Avenida de la Reforma in Mexico City, may be one of Lee's concepts for the Chapultepec Theatre (see 12401-12408) in Mexico City, which was located on the Avenida de la Reforma. The collection contains no photographs of the exterior of the Chapultepec.
    - Reseda Theatre. - Reseda., 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ritz Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - RKO Theatre. - Los Angeles., 1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Rosemead Theatre - Rosemead. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Roxie Theatre. - Los Angeles., 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Silverlake Theatre. - Los Angeles., 1940 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - State Theatre - Pomona. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - State Theatre. - San Diego, 1939-1940; Auditorium front (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Lee creates a powerful perspective leading toward the screen by embellishing the walls with flowing wave designs and using ceiling panels that converge above the proscenium.
    - State Theatre. - San Diego, 1939-1940; Auditorium ceiling (Box 6, Folder 10)
      This view of the ceiling shows how Lee enhanced the simple auditorium space with indirect lighting hidden behind the strong curves of the ceiling panels, which were also painted with large-scale swirling designs. The strong symmetry is broken by the center panel, which is purposefully asymmetrical.
    - State Theatre. - San Diego, 1939-1940; Auditorium front side (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Scalloped forms conceal indirect lighting along the side walls. The wave forms above reach gigantic proportions as they crash into the proscenium, where the waves become a relief sculpture framing the proscenium arch and the motion picture screen.
    - State Theatre. - San Diego, 1939-1940; Facade night (Box 6, Folder 10)
      The tower is clearly borrowed from Lee's Academy Theatre in Inglewood (1939). This night photograph shows how effective Lee's lighting design was at night.
    - State Theatre - Stockton. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - State Theatre. - Stockton, 1936; Existing, marquee (Box 6, Folder 11)
      These photographs of the State Theatre in Stockton show a early twentieth-century theatre that was used for stage acts and movies. These photographs were in Lee's collection, because he was asked to submit a proposal for remodeling. The collection contains no records of his remodeling concepts.
    - State Theatre. - Stockton, 1936; Existing, box office (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - State Theatre. - Stockton, 1936; Existing, auditorium front (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - State Theatre. - Stockton, 1936; Existing, auditorium rear (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Drinking fountain (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Candy vending machines of elaborate Art Deco design contrast with the sleek black surround of the drinking fountain.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Lounge entry (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Automatic photo machines and automatic vending machines epitomized the automatic theme of the Studio. The wallpaper with nude silhouettes added to the stylish atmosphere.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Facade (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Lee's Moderne theatre façade set into the façade of a French Revival style building located next to a Spanish Colonial style building on Sunset Boulevard in Hollywood epitomizes the competition of forms for attention on the commercial streetscape of Los Angeles.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Air conditioning system (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Revealing the mechanical equipment through a glass wall was an innovation in 1931.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Perspective sketch (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Another rendering of the Art Deco façade.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Perspective sketch (Box 6, Folder 12)
      This hard-edged rendering presents a sleek, brightly illuminated concept for the Studio Theatre.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Photo collage (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Published photographs of the finished theatre show how Lee used both styles by combining sleek lines with angular abstract patterns. The upward slanting marquee creates in lights the elaborate pattern of overlapping circles that stands out in the daylight.
    - Studio Theatre. - Hollywood, 1931; Perspective sketch (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Lee's concept for this small, jewel-box like theatre was to create a rich Art Deco façade. Called an automatic theatre the theatre had automatic vending machines and other innovations. Sketches for the design (237001-237009) show both interior and exterior schemes and details.
    - Sunkist Theatre. - Pomona., 1931 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Temple Theatre. - Temple City., 1940 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Sierra Theatre - Delano. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Newman Theatre - Newman. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Nicaragua Theatre - Managua, Nicaragua. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - North Long Beach Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Santa Ana Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Santa Maria Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Woodland Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Woodland, Theatre no.2. - Woodland. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Rialto Theatre - (Becchetti), Cottonwood, Arizona. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Calvi Theatre. - Lennox, California, 1940; Front elevation, sketch (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Schreiber Theatre. (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Wurlitzer Theatre. - Cincinnati, Ohio, 1928; Elevation Alternate design[1] (Box 6, Folder 26)
      Lee did two schemes for this theatre, office tower, and retail complex, planned for Cincinnati. Many studies for the design are also included in the collection.
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Auditorium, side rear (Box 6, Folder 27)
      Designed for a working class community in Los Angeles, the Tower Theater is a modest design which presents a stylish black and white Deco exterior (62701). The night view shows the effective use of neon and spotlighting to illuminate the fluted Moderne tower (62702). The box office is surrounded by circles of light bulbs on the lobby ceiling and a sunburst design on the lobby's terrazzo floor (62703). Poster cases are framed by scrolled pediments and simulated columns. The interior uses exaggerated columns, mirrors, white traditional-style furniture, and gilt to suggest a palatial elegance that is distant from the lives of the theatre's clientele (62704-62705). Hanging lanterns and striped upholstery in the auditorium impart a subdued elegance (62706- 62707).
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Facade day (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Facade night (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Box office (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Foyer (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre - Compton. (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Auditorium, front (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Compton, 1935-1936; Lounge entry (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Etched glass panel (Box 6, Folder 28)
      The etched glass panel depicts a hunter with bow and arrow, a wounded stag and a hunting dog. Lee used this motif in other theatres, such as the Miami Theatre, although the motif seems to bear no relationship to any particular wider theme. The depiction itself, however, suggests a moving picture, with several exposures or frames overlaid on each other.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Detail, painted panel (Box 6, Folder 28)
      A close-up of the glowing panels reveals that they are not just organic leaf forms. The shapes depict a female nude facing a serpent spiraling up the leaves.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Auditorium toward proscenium. Decorations in fluorescent paint (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Note on reverse: Decorations in fluorescent paint, when illuminated by black light, concealed in fixtures, are visible with main lights turned off. Graded shades of blue; ceiling, blue; panels, silver field, fluorescent black ---lighted panels.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Exterior day (Box 6, Folder 28)
      The streamlined form of the building accented by a tall tower is similar to concepts for the De Anza in Riverside and the Linda Vista in Mexico City.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Foyer (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Lee uses curved walls and a curved staircase accentuated by the curved ceiling panels that conceal the indirect lighting.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Exterior night (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Lee's use of neon was especially effective in this tower with its starburst top, similar to the one at the Alex Theatre in Glendale (10301). Probably the starburst flashed on and off in different colors, creating a beacon for moviegoers.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Auditorium (Box 6, Folder 28)
      The auditorium walls curve to enclose the audience. Horizontal lines along the wall accentuate the curves.
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Lobby (Box 6, Folder 28)
      The curves in the design of the terrazzo floor are repeated in the curves of the neon tubing on the ceiling. The neon would have been especially effective at night.
    - Tower Theatre - Fresno. (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Tower Theatre. - Fresno, 1938-1939; Auditorium entrance (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Construction exterior August 2, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Construction photos show the odd open steel frame along the top of the building to give it increased strength (70104), the scaffolding along the Broadway elevation (70105), a view down into the interior showing the steel framing (70106), and the process of applying the finish decoration on the balcony interior (70107).
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Construction view from above May 9, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tower Theatre - Los Angeles. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Auditorium, decoration (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Comparison with the construction photo (70107) shows how the layers of decoration were built up with plaster, perhaps some cast stone pieces and then elaborate painted designs. The panels clearly represent windows, temporarily curtained for the duration of the performance.
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Perspective sketch, colored (Box 7, Folder 1)
      This rendering of the Tower Theatre, Lee's first theatre design, shows how effectively he was able to use the narrow lot crowded on both sides by taller buildings. The tower located at the corner advertised the theatre to the public.
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Exterior (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Lee uses elements of religious architecture, such as the tower, central niche with a statue, the large arched opening and the rows of window along the side of the building, as though to bring as much light into the building as possible, although exactly the opposite was true.
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Construction interior July 16, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Theatre Plans (reverse of 0070102 ). (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tower Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1926-27; Construction exterior August 3, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tower Theatre - Santa Rosa. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Toys Theatre. - Helena, Montana., 1941 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Tujunga Theatre. - Tujunga., 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Auditorium (Box 7, Folder 5)
      The interior of the auditorium featured open trusses, exposed rafters and utilitarian metal light fixtures to lend authenticity to the building. Murals of cowboys and cattle along the side walls added a touch of Hollywood.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Exterior night (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Lee illuminated the barn to highlight its forms in light and dark. The windmill tower with its illuminated revolving wheel attracted attention from afar, while the tower structure was used to display the name of the theatre. For good measure, a standard box sign on a pylon was added at the street frontage.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Perspective sketch Architect's original conception (Box 7, Folder 5)
      One of Lee's few realized theme theatres (as in theme restaurant), the Tumbleweed recreates for recent immigrants to Los Angeles the farmstead of the Great Plains. Built on a large site in the rural suburb of El Monte, the theatre's auditorium takes the form of a Midwestern barn, with buttress-like dormers. To attract attention to the theatre, Lee used the form of the Plains windmill, a feature used at every farm to pump water from an underground well. Note on reverse: Architect's original conception --- Note how closely the finished building matches the rendering.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Aerial view (Box 7, Folder 5)
      This aerial view of Five Points, an important junction in El Monte, shows the site's potential for future commercial development in a thinly populated area.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Exterior tower (Box 7, Folder 5)
      The windmill tower, built of wood, is a heavier version of the usual graceful metal towers found on the Plains.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Wishing Well (Box 7, Folder 5)
      The wishing well stood in the yard, in front of the veranda attached to front of the barn which served as a marquee.
    - Tumbleweed Theatre. - Five Points (El Monte), 1939; Exterior front Unique Barn Theatre (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Built almost exactly as in the rendering, the Tumbleweed included a wishing well and a rail fence with wagon wheels to complete the farmyard theme.
    - Unicorn Theatre. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Valley Theatre., 1934-1935. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Vern Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1939-1941; Auditorium (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Distinctive grilles on side wall handle return air for ventilation. Shiny metallic painted designs on the ceiling and the walls, as well as the shiny surface of the elaborately draped curtain enhance the air of sleekness.
    - Vern Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1939-1941; Candy counter (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Lee designed an unusual self-serve candy counter, which had a slot for customers to deposit 5 cents. Fluorescent lamps illuminate the plaster hood above the candy counter. The hood directs cool air from the air conditioning system over the candy, preventing chocolates from turning color.